# KALIE KNECHT

Berkeley, CA · kalie@berkeley.edu · +1 (304) 989-7626 · https://www.linkedin.com/in/kalieknecht/

# Objective

I am a first year graduate student at UC Berkeley wishing to share and develop skills through research internships. My interests in the nuclear engineering field are **radiation detection** for applications in **nuclear safeguards**, **security**, **and nonproliferation**.

## EDUCATION

## University of California

Berkeley, CA

Doctor of Philosophy in Nuclear Engineering

August 2019 - Present

• Nuclear Science and Security Consortium Fellow

• Minors: Public Policy and Computer Science

## University of Tennessee

Knoxville, TN

Bachelor's of Science in Honors Nuclear Engineering GPA: 3.96

August 2014 - May 2019

• Completed a reactor physics laboratory using the VR-1 reactor at the Czech Technical University

• Visited the Vienna United Nations complex and attended talks by the IAEA and CTBTO

#### SKILLS

Programming Languages: Python, Fortran, and C++
Code Proficiencies: MCNP, GOTHIC, and Cyclus

Software: Microsoft Office, OriginPro, CrystalDiffract, MATLAB, and CMPR

Operating Systems: Windows, Mac, and Linux

Laboratory Skills: Solid State Sample Synthesis and X-ray Diffraction

#### EXPERIENCE

# Oak Ridge National Laboratory

Oak Ridge, TN

Safeguards & Security Technology Intern

May 2019 - August 2019

- Investigated current international safeguards methods for research reactors.
- Collected data from HFIR-REDC Pu-238 production process to determine characteristics of normal operation at a research reactor with adjacent hot cell facilities.

### **Argonne National Laboratory**

Lemont, IL

Nuclear Science & Engineering Intern

May 2018 - August 2018

- Developed code in Fortran to update SAS4A/SASSYS-1 input preprocessor to allow free format input.
- Extended unit testing capabilities of SAS4A/SASSYS-1.

# University of Tennessee

Knoxville, TN

Undergraduate Teaching Assistant

August 2018 - May 2019

- Developed weekly review sessions for Thermal Science and Reactor Theory courses.
- Provided tutoring services for students enrolled in Thermal Science and Reactor Theory.

 $Nuclear\ Engineering\ Undergraduate\ Research\ Assistant$ 

January 2017 - May 2019

- Evaluated transition from an open to closed nuclear fuel cycle using Cyclus.
- Interpreted data collected from Cyclus using Python.

Materials Science & Engineering Undergraduate Research Assistant

May 2015 - January 2017

- Synthesized a sample for study using conventional solid-state synthesis.
- Conducted an in-situ high temperature x-ray diffraction (XRD) study and analyzed XRD patterns.
- Created and presented a poster with a summary of all work and results at The Minerals, Metals, and Materials Society national conference in 2016.

# **Dominion Energy**

Richmond, VA

Nuclear Safety Analysis Intern

May 2017 - August 2017

- Analyzed Time to Core Boil (TTCB) for various RCS conditions in GOTHIC thermal-hydraulic code resulting in more accurate TTCB estimates.
- Communicated with Surry personnel to present TTCB analysis and results in a way that would be most easily used by plant operators.

Nuclear Spent Fuel Intern

August 2016 - December 2016

- Created a database of Millstone Power Station spent fuel that allows engineers to extract data for dry storage more efficiently, reducing engineering work time by at least 50%.
- Examined fuel anomalies in North Anna fuel assemblies to qualify them for dry storage.

Nuclear Core Design Intern

January 2016 - May 2016

- Reported burnup, isotopic, and monthly core follow data and ensured plant was operating as expected.
- Used CASMO to model new Surry Power Station fuel assemblies.
- Analyzed control rod drop times during startup physics testing at North Anna Unit 2.

## LEADERSHIP

# Society of Women Engineers

President of UTK SWE

May 2018 - May 2019

- Raised \$11,450 for section through company sponsorships and award applications.
- Managed team of 7 officers and 10 chairs overseeing 260 member section.
- Created Alumni Chair position to improve relations with UTK SWE Alumni.

# UTK Nuclear Engineering Department

 $Student\ Ambassador$ 

August 2015 - May 2019

- Led tours of Nuclear Engineering facilities for prospective undergraduate and graduate students.
- Received 'Outstanding Ambassador' Award for 2017-2018 academic year.

#### **American Nuclear Society**

Secretary of UTK ANS

May 2017 - May 2018

- Developed a points system to track the number of events that members attend and reward highly involved members with a scholarship at the end of the academic year.
- Coordinated with nearby high school to teach a lecture about nuclear technology.

### Women in Nuclear

Secretary of UTK WIN

May 2016 - May 2017

- Organized a panel discussion meeting highlight co-op and internship experiences of nuclear engineering students.
- Coordinated an event with other engineering societies to prepare students for a job fair with workshops on elevator pitches, mock interviews, and resume critiques.

# Honors and Awards

Department of Energy Integrated University Program Graduate Fellowship at University of Wisconsin. Declined offer.	March 2019
American Nuclear Society	
Charles Thomas Memorial Scholarship	May 2018
Undergraduate Scholarship	May 2017
Operations & Power Division Scholarship	May 2016
University of Tennessee Department of Nuclear Engineering	
Top Senior Academic Award	May 2019
Top Junior Academic Award	May 2018
Top Sophomore Academic Award	May 2017